[Music]
I was wrong this ceremony begins timely
as uh ever there was a drum roll for the
royal family that proceeded onto stage
[Music]
everybody Rises for the Nobel laurates
entering the stage here to the tunes of
Wolf Gang Amad MOS
[Music]
AR and D major by Vol gang abos mosad
performed by the Royal stockh
philarmonic Orchestra under the batn of
Alexander Hanson and now your majesties
opening your Royal
highnesses esteemed Nobel Prize
laurates excellencies ladies and Gent
gentlemen on behalf of the Nobel
Foundation it is my great honor and
pleasure to welcome you all to the 2023
Nobel Prize award
ceremony in particular I wish to welcome
the Nobel Prize laurates their families
and
friends earlier today in
Oslo nargas muhamadi was awarded the
Nobel Peace Prize in her absence and I
quote for her fight against the
oppression of women and in Iran and her
fight to promote Human Rights and
freedom for all end of
quote her absence was due to her being
imprisoned together with many other
prisoners of conscience in the notorious
Evan prison in
tran in spite of these
circumstances her strong message
smuggled out of prison and read by her
children is finally one of
Hope Victory is not easy but it is
certain we look forward to receiving her
family here in Stockholm in a few
days the message of Alfred Nobel
transmitted to us through his will is
equally
clear he believed in the unique powers
of science literature and action for
peace to help transform the world to the
benefit of
humankind and for all of
this International collaboration and
respect for knowledge are
key I'm convinced that this message is
all the more important since it may seem
untimely today
when the optimism of nobel's time is
being replaced by radical pessimism or
even
resignation and when new interconnected
crisis challenge our understanding of
our mission in Academia culture and
Civil
Society but on the contrary I'm
convinced that at this moment in history
with increasingly polarized views which
tend to our societies a part with
democracies being undermined and with
Wars and conflicts throughout the world
which continue to cause so many victims
we need more than ever to keep nobel's
vision in
mind he believed in knowledge
Enlightenment and the pursuit of
Truth the development of our world is
not decided by
Destiny it lies in our own power to
decide on our future and on how to
transmit Our Heritage to new
generations our new capacities as
humankind both with
digitization which makes the world come
closer than ever and with artificial
intelligence which contains Endless
Possibilities as well as risks need to
be addressed both scientifically and
culturally
through free fundamental research
science explores and expands the frontes
of human knowledge laying the
foundations for applications and
development work and thus also providing
preparedness for unexpected and
unpredictable future events in our
world the scientific breakthroughs
awarded this year the physics prize for
EXP experment with light which capture
the shortest of moments the chemistry
prize for the discovery and synthesis of
quantum dots or the groundbreaking
findings behind the prize in physiology
or medicine that enabled the development
of effective mRNA
vaccines and for the price in economic
Sciences research uncovering key drivers
of gender differences in the labor
market all serve as powerful examples of
the importance of forerunners who pave
the way as well as of the manifold
phases of
science together we see their
strength last but certainly not least
the prize in literature
explores through what I'm tempted to
call fundamental research in literature
the boundaries of human existence by
giving voice to the
unable the laurates being awarded
tonight each in a unique way testify to
the power of Science and
literature they show us that
individually and together we have it
within ourselves to change the
world Professor Aid C leing chair of the
board of the Nobel
[Applause]
Foundation now evening serate from
silent music by Valentine sylvestro
[Music]
am
evening serenate composed by Ukrainian
composer Valentine
sylvestro Valentin sylvestro who has
been living in Berlin since the Russian
invasion in February
22 now presentation speech by Professor
Eva Olson it's time for for the physics
price your majesties your Royal
highnesses esteemed Nobel Prize laurates
your excellencies ladies and
gentlemen the world is Big so
big bigger than you ever can
imagine those are the words of zakaras
topelius and they illustrate the fact
that we are part of a vast
Universe the universe that we are
exploring but the vast and the big is
governed by the very small
details the small details that are
beyond the capabilities of our five
traditional senses of sight smell touch
taste and
hearing these small details have great
impact on our lives and offer intriguing
possibilities for expanding our
knowledge they give us the power to
design materials and methods for
exploration for future
sustainability and for promoting
Health this applies to both length and
and time scale when we talk about the
small
details this year's Nobel Prize in
physics is focused on small time scales
and to be precise the at of
seconds a
heartbeat lasts for 1 thousand thousand
thousand thousand thousand and thousand
to
seconds that is the same number of
seconds since our
universe was
born the up second is the scale of the
world of the electrons a world that we
now can explore back in
1925 vaner Heisenberg argued that this
world cannot be
seen but thanks to utto second light
buls is this is starting to
change the challenge was an extremely
short time scale it took several decades
to overcome this barrier AOS second
science allows us to address fundamental
questions such as the time scale of the
photo electric effect for which Albert
Einstein received the Nobel Prize in
physics in 1921
with UT Toc pulses we can study how the
distribution of electrons oscillates
within molecules and
materials the information about charge
fluctuations holds secrets and solutions
to how to control electronic
migration with to Second chemistry
specific chemical bonds can be
selectively broken or
formed giving us a control to tailor new
materials with aosc physics we can study
charge transfer processes in materials
and they are the key elements on in the
function and optimization of solar cells
batteries catalysts and
electronics as a few
examples the origin of this year's prize
can be traced to the late 1970s
and the early
1980s when atoms in strong laser Fields
were
studied our lades discovered that it was
possible to generate up Toc light pulses
by controlling the interaction between
lasers and atoms they developed methods
for measuring the duration of these
pulses they also develop techniques for
generating both pulse trains and
individual
PES emiritus professor
augustini professor Dr Krauss and
Professor an
ler you have been awarded the 2023 Nobel
Prize in physics for experimental
methods that generate atosc impulses of
light for the study of electron Dynamics
in matter
it is an honor and a privilege to convey
to you the warmest congratulations of
the royal Swedish Academy of
Sciences I now ask you to step forward
to receive the Nobel Prize from the
hands of his majesty the king
first Professor augustini born in
Tunisia Affiliated to the Ohio state
university in the United States of
America
[Music]
happy family
members Professor
Krauss born in Hungary Affiliated to the
max plank Institute and the ludik
maximilians university in Germany
[Music]
and an L born in France in Paris
currently working at the Lund University
in Sweden
[Music]
after this Str Round of Applause it is
time for the prize in chemistry and a
speech by Professor Hiner
link your majesties your Royal
highnesses esteemed Nobel Prize laurates
ladies and
gentlemen materials can have strikingly
different properties
for example materials can be hard soft
or
brittle they can be transparent
reflective or
colored they can conduct electricity and
heat or they can be good
insulators they can be magnetic or
non-magnetic or melt at high or at low
temperatures when humans have discovered
new
materials they have often fundamentally
changed our society early examples are
bronze Iron and
Steel the currently ongoing digital
transformation and electrification are
enabled by semiconductors and Battery
materials traditionally to create a new
material we choose new chemical and
structural compositions that means we
order atoms in new
constellations however early in the 20th
century very soon after the development
of quantum theory a striking prediction
was
made according to Quantum Mechanics the
properties of a material could be
completely
changed if it was made so small that it
was only a few atoms
across in other words it should be
possible to modify a material's
properties just by adjusting its size
without changing its
composition for example if particles
were made small enough to squeeze
together the electron's quantum
wave the electron should be able to
store more energy and which they could
then release to a bright Photon so that
larger particles would emit red light
and smaller particles blue
light let me illustrate this if you
think of my fingernails as materials you
can see they have different sizes but
they look all the same if they were at
the Nano scale then a large fingernail
might look red a smaller one might look
blue and with all colors in
between for several decades this
remained a purely theoretical prediction
it seemed almost impossible to make
particles consisting of a specific
number of atoms with the required
perfect crystallinity and pristine
surfaces Alexa yakimov solved this
challenge using using glass making
methods during the cooling process of
molten glass he managed to create copper
chloride crystals whose color varied
with size precisely as predicted by
quantum
mechanics he had discovered that it was
possible to make Quantum
dots Lis Bru paved the way to producing
Quantum dots that were free in solution
using standard chemical
methods his Discovery triggered a wave
of interest in learning how to make
these new Nano structures these new Nano
materials and in using them for exciting
applications at first however it was
difficult to produce Quantum dots of
sufficiently high quality and in large
enough
quantities mongji bendi developed an
ingenious chemical method that produced
very high quality Quantum dots that was
that could be modified to create more
complex structures and was scalable to
industrial production
levels the discoveries of this year's
laurates have made decisive
contributions to the interdisciplinary
field of Nano science nanot techn
technology is about making structures a
thousand times smaller than the Strand
than a strand of hair and using them for
better safer and more powerful devices
and
Technologies Quantum dots specifically
are used to explore the inner life of
biological cells to improve screens and
the quality of energy saving lead
lighting and to Mark tumor tissue during
surgery there's also intensive Research
into using Quantum dots for improved
solar cells in flexible Electronics or
in future Quantum
communication mji bendi l Bruce and
Alexa
yakimov your discovery of quantum dots
and how to make them has opened up a new
way of Designing materials
and helped catalyze the field of
nanoscience this is a truly great
achievement for the benefit of humankind
on behalf of the royal Swedish Academy
of Sciences I wish to convey you our
warmest
congratulations may I now ask you to
step forward and receive your Nobel
prizes from the hands of his majesty the
king
first Professor
bendi born in France Paris Affiliated to
MIT in the United States
[Music]
[Applause]
Professor brew an American at the
Columbia University in New York receives
the prize from the Swedish King
[Music]
[Applause]
and third laurate in chemistry Alexa
yakimov of Russian origin nowadays
living and working in the United States
of America
[Music]
[Applause]
now time for some
music from L by French composer ector so
[Music]
you for
so FL
[Music]
for
as
[Music]
[Applause]
k
[Music]
spe
I neede
[Music]
is your
a for
[Music]
seee
sopr julas
pan to the tunes of L by ector bero
French
composer and now onwards to the Nobel
Prize in physiology or
medicine your majesties your Royal
highnesses esteemed Nobel Prize laurates
gentle uh ladies and
gentlemen DNA is the genetic blueprint
that defines what we are a fish a
honeybee a lementary or
human RNA is less well known but equally
important messenger RNA or
mRNA carries genetic information and
acts as a template for protein
production thousands of different mRNA
molecules are present in each of our
cells at any given time in instructing
the cells how to develop and what
functions to execute
conversion of DNA to mRNA to protein is
an evolutionary concered process that is
common to all forms of
life messenger RNA was first defined by
Jacob and Mano in
1961 a discovery that was awarded with
the Nobel Prize in physiology or
medicine in
1965 although the identity and function
of mRNA has been known for over 60
years and mRNA is routinely used in most
modern Medical Research
Laboratories the term has remained
largely obscure outside the scientific
Community until
recently this year's Nobel Prize
laurates in physiology or medicine
Professor Catalin kerico and Professor
Drew Weissman have ensured that the term
mRNA is now broadly recognized
most of us present here today have
received one or several mRNA vaccine
doses in our arm a process that directs
some of our cells to produce the encoded
protein for a short
while if the M codes of foreign virus
protein such as in the case of the covid
vaccines this will alert our immune
system to stimulate a response against
the virus protecting us against disease
should we later become infected
RNA molecules are elegantly simple in
their composition with just four
building blocks nucleotides linked
together in different order to encode
any protein of
Interest cathaline kico an expert mRNA
biochemist Andrew Weissman a skilled
immunologist shared a vision of using
mRNA as a generic carrier of information
for clinical applications
but early results showed limited
success carico and Weissman realized
that to achieve their goal they needed
to understand how our cells respond to
different forms of RNA at the molecular
level in a breakthrough Discovery
published in 2005 they demonstrated that
mRNA produced with standard nucleotides
evoked an undesired inflammatory
response in our cells
they found that this reaction was
circumvented when one of the four
nucleotides was chemically modified to
mimic our own
mRNA this finding provided a solution to
a major problem previously facing all
mRNA based clinical
applications propelling the MRNA
technology into a whole new
era the discovery by this year's Nobel
Prize laurates in physiology or medicine
surprisingly enabled the development of
effective vaccines that helped control a
devastating pandemic and save millions
of Life 15 years later in
2020 the scientific Community together
with governments the private sector and
Regulatory authorities demonstrated that
it's possible to greatly reduce the time
needed for vaccine development in
situations where this is urgently
needed science communication is
challenging a silver lining all the
pandemic was the opportunity to increase
Public's awareness and knowledge about
infectious threats and how our immune
system
functions terms like mRNA virus variants
antibodies t- cells and B cells are now
uh common to most most people understand
these
terms and surveys demonstrate that the
Public's trust in scientific research
increased
during the
pandemic the basic research performed by
the 2023 laurates in uh physiology or
medicine no doubt contributed to
this this year's prize is very much in
the spirit of Alfred
Nobel a groundbreaking contribution to
the greatest benefit of
humankind dear professors K Co and
Weissman on behalf of the Nobel assembly
at kolinska instituted
it's my great joy and privilege to
convey to you our warmest
congratulations I invite you now to step
forward to receive the Nobel Prize from
the hands of his majesty the
King speech by Professor Gila calls on
here the stum and first to receive the
medicine prize is uh cathalene
carico born in Hungary Affiliated to the
shed University in Hungary and the
University of Pennsylvania and the
United
[Music]
States Drew Weissman American working at
the pen Institute for RNA Innovations
and the University of
Pennsylvania yes given how the research
has uh had implications for the fight of
Co it's truly in the spirit of the will
of Alfred Nobel that originally stated
that the price should go to discoveries
that have benefited mankind the most
during the past
[Applause]
year before we move on to the literature
prize another musical in
from judita by
[Music]
France
for
spe
[Music]
fore foree
those
[Music]
Christan
la
[Music]
spee
spee feel
[Music]
son
heart the
[Music]
those on
soprano Yulia span and a liberetto by
kler and fitzon B and here we have Yun
Foster about to receive his price in
literature after a speech by
uh the Swedish
Academy's professor andeson
foreign foreign fore
[Music]
in English then whether in Pros drama or
poetry his writing approaches a state of
uncertainty that can open a relation to
the
Divine with commonplace words here
seeming inadequate F's rare quality is
that he succeeds as the award citation
reads in giving voice to the UN
sayable early on in his authorship fer
captures the unsayable in his short Pros
piece I couldn't say to you from
1991 where we meet an old man who is
unable to rid himself of the vivid
memory of something he has failed to say
to his beloved throughout all these
years together he has not Forten her
look in her eyes as she sits alone at
the table in the school cafeteria memory
that remains lodged in his mind from
that day
forward this is the case even on her
deathbed words and life have drifted
apart but when fer allows the old man to
voice the unsaid The Impossible is
transformed into both a touching elgy
and a triumph over speech
the late Masterpiece septology completed
in
2021 the main character ASA is an
elderly artist who in the spirit of the
medieval Christian Mystic mea
eart turns in prayer to a god beyond all
Concepts and
ideas both in the previously mentioned
early piece and here in this late novel
the protagonist is nevertheless filled
with anxiety which creates a tension
between the mundane and the
Divine it is this anxiety that lends the
work its internal
drama yunos is not a difficult writer he
uses the simplest of words and writes
about experiences to which we can all
relate
separation death and the vulnerability
of love any difficulty with also rather
concerns our Readiness to open ourselves
to the existential uncertainty upon
which he constantly
touches but the fact that he is one of
today's most widely performed
playwrights indicates that this is a
torment shared by
many what is remarkable about fer
Simplicity is that it gains death and
intensity through repetition and
variation in his har the early novel
closed guitar in which a mother locks
herself out of a flat and becomes
separated from her baby daughter a sense
of panic emerges into the language
form in the shimmering world of morning
and evening anxiety turns to wonder and
profound consolation as an old man
Johannes awakes one morning to find he's
dying and begins to lose his sense of
reality
in septology the rolling Pros devoid of
sentence breaks become one of them
painter asess wandering thought drawing
in the reader with hypnotic
power either F focuses on the unable as
in these works or he chooses the
language of
sence as in his radical renewal of world
drama during the
1990s beginning with is going to come
the play with which he made his
International breakthrough he discovers
the possibility of allowing
speechlessness to materialize on stage
in the theater all this is internal must
be revealed and what cannot be said must
too be given a
voice it is demonstrated in a long
series of emotionally charged plays that
includes the name dream of Autumn and
death
variations here time expands to allow
the dead to take their place on
stage y y foser is the first Nobel Prize
laurate in literature to write in newos
and like his great
Norwegian predecessor tesos he combines
strong local
ties with a belief in the possibilities
of contemporary
literature he shies away from what we
might consider to be definitive wording
making it almost impossible to quote him
as such he is the master of ambivalence
and of the
unsolved in his world uncertainty pulses
with a secret
light Dear John
foser allow me to convey the warm
congratulations of the Swedish Academy
while asking you to step forward to
receive from the hand of his majesty the
king the price in literature
[Music]
y fosa was born in hagun then grew up in
strand outside Bergen on the Norwegian
Westland and uh fittingly we will now be
listening to some music by Edward grig
the Norwegian composer and pianist who
is widely considered one of the leading
Romantic Era
composers Greg who
himself came from that region born in B
again the pieces Anitra St from pan
toage March
[Music]
e
la
[Music]
for
[Applause]
this homage March is the third part of
Edward GG's work sigur yourself
far and now we are
arriving at the last station on this
trip it is time for the serious Rick
Bank prize in economic Sciences in
memory of Alfred Nobel after speech by
professor your Royal highnesses esteemed
Nobel Prize FL
ladies and
gentlemen it is about
time this year's price in economic
Sciences is essentially about time time
should have the potential to be a great
equalizer everybody gets the same daily
allowance and get to choose how to spend
it but although the length of the day is
equally distributed its span is often
not enough uh for for the pursuit of
life many goals because raising children
takes time engaging in a long
educational program takes time investing
in a career climbing the promotional
ladder takes
time Claudia golden explains that women
had to make choices about time under
different constraints than men these
choices had economic underpinnings and
were appropriate given the circumstances
of the time and the ability of women to
peer accurately into the future the
result however has been unequal outcomes
in how much time women spend working in
the labor force in how much they earn
when they
work it is about time because living
conditions change over time golden shows
how a host of technological advances in
the home refrigerators vacuum cleaners
and washing machines freed up women's
time during the past Century she
explains how the emergence of birth Bild
controls in the 196 60s improved women's
ability to plan career and family as a
result the rate of women entering the
labor market tripled in many countries
undeniably one of the largest economic
and social changes of modern
times but can we expect that the mere
passage of time will do the trick
Claudia golden tells us that
historically this has not been the case
she digs deeply into the archives and
reveals the various type of work carried
out by female professionals who were not
listed with occupations in historical
censuses but they were butchers Bakers
seamstresses shoe makers peers Coopers
Putters template workers glass engravers
and iron mongers just to mention a few
despite being absent from official
records these women carried out their
work within industrialization these
professions became rarer among women and
during 200 years of American history
fale labor market participation
decreased before it increased time
served as a divider before it became an
equalizer it is about time because
change takes time Golden's work teaches
us that history progresses slowly as
each generation achieves its own formost
success then passes the Baton to the
next on a winter day in Chicago in 1971
a baton was surely passed a young woman
dressed in high boots and a fashionably
short coat that barely covered her mini
skirt observed a gray-haired woman a
retired Professor walking to the
computer center carrying a large box of
Punch Cards the two women were separated
by more than their age and by more than
their fashion sense but they occupied
the same moment in
time what the young woman learned from
the older one was that women could have
the same commitment to research as male
professors she saw a vision of the
possible and felt the desire to achieve
what was lacking in her book career and
family golden recalls this moment as an
appetition a reminder of the past and a
vision of the future at the same
time today a win today in stockolm will
forever be another historical moment
Professor Claudia golden it is about
time that the world learns the long work
history of half its population your
research has radically change what we
know about women in the labor market and
how we understand what we know today we
celebrate your pathbreaking academic
achievements they are more than a baton
to be passed they are giant shoulders
for which coming Generations will be
able to see very
far it is an honor and a privilege to
convey to you on behalf of the royal
Swedish Academy of Sciences our warmest
congratulations may I now please ask you
to step forward and receive your prize
from the Majesty the
king Professor Claudia golden who lives
in Boston and works at the har at
Harvard
University is the third woman to receive
the prize in
economics out of a total of 93 laurates
so far
[Applause]
standing ovations for the lit and now
the Swedish national anthem
[Music]
the
in
[Music]
and now it's time for the guests to
leave the a torium to the queen of
shiba's festivity March by Hugo Alan
[Music]
thank you for this year's prize ceremony
here from
Stockholm welcome back next year
[Music]
[Applause]